Okay. Uh we are going to continue our
scaling journey. Uh today's a bit of a
grabag of stuff. I mean, we're really
going to talk about some of the more
advanced details of scaling laws and how
we scale up models. Um and in doing so,
we're going to cover what I feel like
are some important details in how, you
know, you would scale up a language
model in practice. Okay. So, you know,
we might want to ask some questions like
is the scaling loss stuff that you
talked about two lectures ago, you know,
does it actually work at real building
open source model scales? Um, it would
be nice if we could optimize some of
this. There's a lot of like learning
rate tricks and other things that people
do um that I think you should know as
people that are informed about how to
build uh language models. So, we'll talk
about some of these optimization
details. Um and then I think the last
thing I want to talk about is when we
scale up there are certain things that
are going to be a little bit trickier to
tune. Um we know that optimizers and
optimizer behavior is going to be
actually pretty scale sensitive and
because of that things like
initializations, learning rates, batch
size, those we need to carefully think
about as a function of scale. So we will
talk about how to think about those um
carefully.
Okay. So up until now most of our
discussions uh what I would is what I
would call like the classical you know
scaling laws cannon we talked about
Kaplan we talked about oh even hess um
and then you know the chinchilla paper
right so so we're up to date with I
don't know 2022 or something um since
then you know there have been a number
of scaling papers that are published by
people who train big models um although
I think the number of such papers have
decreased in recent years and most of
them have come out of the open source
community in China. Um, and so today I
want to talk about um, a number of these
that I've sort of curated and selected
um, to give you a sense of, you know,
what does scaling at the frontier, at
least open frontier look like? Um, what
are the things that these people care
about or worry about and like what would
what would you need to do to sort of
speedrun your way from Kinchilla all the
way to let's say Kimmy K2 um, most
recent release that has some scaling
details. Okay, so that's going to be the
first part of this lecture. We're going
to go through a couple papers and we're
going to go through the details. The
second part is going to be a discussion
of um optimizers and initializations. Um
and remember I spent a non-trivial
amount of time um two lectures ago on
the selection of batch sizes. Um that's
going to be an important factor and it's
also going to be important um thinking
about how we're going to tune things
like learning rates. Those are very
sensitive um very important to get
right. And so it turns out that a lot of
effort has been invested into getting
those things right. and we will talk
about some of the techniques to do so.
And this may in fact even be useful in
your day-to-day lives of training um
various language models because they'll
give you a sense of how to change your
hyperparameters in your experiments as
you scale up or down. Okay. Um so I'm
going to spend a non-trivial amount of
time talking about two papers in
particular. Um they're not the newest
papers. Um they're not necessarily the
most actually Deep Seek one might be one
of the more detailed ones. um most
detailed scaling paper in general, but I
think this is hits a sweet spot. So both
of these papers are kind of serious
scaling investigations from people who
build you know reasonably high
performance models and importantly they
take pretty different approaches to some
of the key questions that we will ask
today and so I think they're a good way
to motivate a lot of the rest of the
lecture. So I'm going to talk about
these two. First one's mini CPM. Um this
was I think back in 2024 high
performance small language model um in
DeepSeek. You all are now familiar with
this. I no longer have to justify why
I'm talking about DeepS which is great.
Um we'll start by talking about mini CPM
though. Um I I do like this paper. Um
especially when it first came out it
felt very fresh and new and like very
you know at the cutting edge. Um even in
2026 I feel like a lot of the things
that the mini CPM folks did is very
informative to us. Um, I'll talk about
this later as I get to the newer papers,
but I think it's kind of becoming the
case that a lot of this like classic
scaling stuff like how you set learning
rates, how do you do chinchilla, um,
those kinds of things I think are now
taken for granted like everyone just
assumes that you know how to do those
things and so people don't really talk
about those as much anymore in the
paper. So it's really nice to talk about
um, some of these like older papers for
that reason. Okay.
Um so mini CPM is an effort by you know
a bunch of industry academic
partnerships folks um over in the
Chinese open source community to come up
with a high performance smallish
language model and at the time when this
came out um it was basically
state-of-the-art for like the 1 to two
billion parameter bracket um nowadays
you know GMA and other models Gemma and
other models at 2B or 3B are going to be
higher performance but these are you
know competitive well-trained models at
least at 2024 standards Um, so how do
you train these models? Okay, as I said
before, um, you know, we have to get
some of these like scaling parameters
right. And one of the things that I'll
talk about today, um, that I'll
emphasize quite a bit, um, is
initializations are very important.
Initializations are important because
they allow you to, um, make certain
hyperparameters less scale dependent. Um
so the first technique that I want to
talk about from this mini CPM paper um
is a special class of initializations
called MUP. Um so MUP the whole point of
this approach is to say I want to make
sure that my optimal learning rate is
the same as I scale up and down. Right?
I talked about this very briefly um in
in the two lectures ago. So you should
hopefully remember that a little bit.
But this is kind of the the first real
instantiation that we're going to talk
about. What does that look like
specifically? Um the mini CPM paper has
a nice list of things you know to do. Um
so they scale the embedding output. They
scale the residual connections by the
square root of number of layers. They
scale the initialization of all their
matrix shaped tensors by the fan out
ratio. Um they scale the learning rates
of tensors and and you know you should
pay attention to this one because this
is exotic if you aren't used to like per
parameter learning rates. Um and then
they also scale the LM heads. We'll talk
about why you do these things or like
how you derive this particular set of
scalings. Um, suffice to say that, you
know, you're just going to change up how
you're going to do your initializations
and your learning rates a little bit in
the hopes of stabilizing your learning
rates a little bit.
Um, and of course we're training a small
model here, but we're still wanting to
do a nice scaling strategy, right? Like
part of the point of this study is not
that you want to brute force, you know,
a 1.5B model by training hundreds of
them. You want to get the
hyperparameters exactly right the first
time. So you're going to train a bunch
of much smaller models um and then get a
scaling ladder up all the way to your
target size um of 5x or so, right? Um
and so there's about a 5x gap between
the biggest model they train on their
ladder and the actual model that they're
going to finally release, right? Um, and
their goal is going to be to nail down,
I think, what most people consider to be
the sensitive parameters like optimal
batch size, learning rate. Um, and then
the token to size ratio that we talked
about at Chinchilla, um, they sort of
also want to replicate a chinchilla
analysis. Much less important to us, um,
now and and probably to you even if
you're training, but I'm going to talk
about it regardless because there's one
important thing in in the way they do
that that I think is very informative
and useful.
Okay, so um as I said earlier, right,
the whole point of going through this
weird initialization or non-standard
initialization called MUP is to try to
make the optimal learning rate stable.
Um is it um at least in sort of the mini
CPM case, the answer is yes. Um in fact,
it's very very clean in their
experiments. They sweep learning rate um
across a variety of models. So each line
is a model size. Um the minimal loss is
basically right on 10 to the -2. Um I
guess the minima slightly shifted for
the smallest model but I mean even then
it's quite close to the minimum. Um so
this is you know a nice success case of
the MUP approach. We will talk about
several other models and other papers
that use MUP. Um this is not the only
way to do it but this is one effective
way to do it. And if you can get
something like this now you've kind of
removed the need to tune the learning
rate.
But of course, even if you have a nice
parameterization that fixes your
learning rate to a single sort of
optimum, your optimal batch size is
still not going to be kind of the same.
So the the batch size actually varies as
a function of uh both data set size and
uh model size. Um so in their case, you
know, they run these sort of model
training run. So each column of points
that you see uh on these plots is a is a
is a training run. So they're they have
a fixed batch size and they increase the
number of tokens processed I guess from
bottom to top. Um and then they ask okay
we've done many of these training runs
what is the optimal batch size fitting
sort of these quadratic sort of curves
onto each of these sort of uh uh lines
over here this sort of equal loss
contour. What they find is sort of this
kind of optimal batch size scaling as a
function of the number of tokens
processed. And they do this across
different model sizes. Um, you know,
maybe you would not be surprised by this
given, you know, the nice scalings that
we saw in the Kaplan paper for critical
batch sizes, but the optimal batch size
does have a sort of power loss structure
with respect to the target loss. Um, and
so we kind of see exactly the Kaplan
style analysis of, you know, if your
loss is lower on the left, your batch
size should be bigger, right? Critical
batch size scaling. Um and so now given
a particular loss target which you can
you know back out from the scaling loss
um you can basically set what the
optimal or you know critical batch sizes
that would give you the best trade-offs.
Right? So there's a nice clean trend
here. This will let you set batch size
very easily and precisely.
Okay. So those two um the batch size and
the learning rate scaling um they're
going to come back over and over again.
Those are arguably the most important
and sensitive parameters to uh do
scaling laws on. Um but I'll talk about
one last thing in the mini CPM paper
that I think is important. Um so you
know remember like to do chinchilla
right we need to train a lot of
different models. So we're going to
let's say do isoflops. That means I'm
going to fix the flops budget and I'm
going to vary you know my trade-offs
between number of tokens uh and model
size. Um and to do that I'm going to
let's say increase the amount of data I
train on. Right? So I increase the
number of sequences. But as I increase
the number of sequences remember that
each one of these gets a different
learning rate schedule. right? You know,
you all training on cosign learning
rates. Cosignine learning rates look
different. You need to know the terminal
sort of total budget before you train in
order to have a cosign schedule, right?
Um and so this leads to kind of a
annoying fact which is that you just
need to keep retraining your models. If
you want to train a you know 8 million
sequence model, right, you can't start
like restart from the end of a 4 million
sequence model, right? You have to just
restart from scratch because your
learning rate schedule is just
fundamentally different, right? And this
is just very annoying. It's like a
quadratic cost in some sense of doing
this um because you have to keep
restarting your runs just from the
start. Um and this seems very wasteful.
Um and I think lots of other people did
too. Um and I think uh one of the nice
solutions from the mini CPM paper uh is
what's now called I think the warm-up
stable decay learning rate or this is
you know the popular term for this. Um
and it's basically a big trapezoid. Um
so you've got a warm-up phase. The
warm-up phase is usually defined as a
constant number of steps, not as a
fraction of your your training target.
Right? So, this is independent of your
training horizon. You've got a fairly
long run where you're holding the
learning rates constant. That's the
stable phase. Um, and then at the end,
you're going to decay fairly rapidly
down to zero, right? That's the decay
phase. Um, and generally, you know, the
decay phase is something like 10 to 20%
of your total training run, right? So,
you're going to be stable for the vast
majority of your training run and then
do a very rapid decay down to usually
about 10% of your maximum uh learning
rate at the very end here. And that's
like a a very typical uh warm-up uh
warm-up stable decay learning rate.
Okay. And why do we do this? What's the
point of doing this? Well, we do WSD
because now we can restart a run at any
point at the end of the stable phase,
right? So, if I want to reuse a run and
like train it for longer, right? I'll
just roll back my training to the last
stable checkpoint. Um, and then I'll
just run the stable learning rates
forward and then red decay the model
down to zero. Right? So this provides a
very easy way for us to essentially run
sort of scale in data experiments
without constantly rerunning uh your
experiments. Right? So you you do have
to reday every time, but that's maybe
10% of the total cost. You know, it's a
much better situation to be repeatedly
decaying than to repeatedly rerun your
pre-training uh runs. And this is this
is a very common trick that's used in
many places. Um I I'll show I guess a
performance comparison. Um there have
been many plots of this form. Um I think
who who was the most recent folks that
were were um uh maybe it was Martin
Jaggy and others. Uh I think over at ETH
had like an extensive study of like WSD
sort of performance. But I think a lot
of papers have shown similar things of
you know you have a well-tuned cosign uh
learning curve. This is you know the
orange line over here. And then you've
got various WSD curves. And WSD curves
always look a little bit funky because
it looks like you're way underperforming
until you hit the decay phase where
suddenly you kind of reclaim all of your
gains and then you sort of match or even
sometimes exceed the cosine learning
rate performance. Um anecdotally, I
think if you if you talk to a bunch of
people training networks, I think a lot
of people will say the cosine is
slightly better in many cases. Um but
WSD is basically as good in many other
situations. Like it is a very versatile
default learning rate. um doesn't
necessarily suffer from having to sort
of rerun uh if you want to just continue
runs. Um it is very cool though to see
you know just how much of an impact
learning rate decay has if you haven't
you know played with that before like it
this part of decaying the learning rate
is just incredibly important to sort of
getting the final sort of annealing
parts of your uh training uh together.
Okay, so that's the comparison there.
Um, okay. So, now that we're equipped
with WSD style learning rates, you know,
chinchilla style analyses are actually
very easy. What you're going to do is
you're going to, you know, essentially
run one long run and then you'll just
sort of rewind the checkpoints and then
repeatedly decay and that will give you
sort of sweeps along the data dimension
and then you'll also do sweeps along the
model dimension. You can do isoflops or
any other kind of analysis that you
would like. Um the mini CPM authors for
whatever reason choose to try to
replicate methods one and three which to
me are the the least reliable of the
chinchilla methods but you know they do
get fairly nicel looking scaling curves.
Um if you look at the mini CPM uh sort
of chinchilla method one they they see
like nice lower envelopes that look
mostly linear across these which is
good. Um and then method three they get
nice smooth scaling for the most part in
both sort of the the compute to
non-mbbedding parameter trade-off. So um
it seems like for the most part they get
reasonable chinchilla looking fits. One
thing I will point out um is that they
get pretty different exponents for their
overall joint fit um compared to
chinchilla. Um they claim in the paper
that this means that they should be
training with way more tech pieces of
text than chinchilla. is highly unclear
to me whether this is uh really true or
whether their chinchilla fits are a
little bit strange relative to um the
original chinchilla paper. Okay, I'll
stop here for one moment in case someone
has questions about mini CPM. Maybe the
main couple things to take away is one
is you know the use of MUP is a useful
trick I guess to try to stabilize how
your learning rate changes over scales
and then the second thing maybe to
remember is the WSD learning rate.
That's just a very common trick you
should all kind of know about this
learning rate. That's a basic, you know,
thing to know. Okay,
good. All right, so then I'll move on to
uh DeepSeek. Um, this is the kind of,
you know, original Deepseek paper. Um,
before, you know, they started talking
about and all these other sort of very
cool things. Um, and I think even at the
very first DeepSseek paper, you could
kind of tell that these were very
serious people because I think Deepseek
LLM, you know, even now is, I think, one
of the more nicely executed scaling
analyses in the open world, right? And I
feel like they have lots of great taste
in the experiments that they run. So
even before you know uh R1 and so on
came out it was like kind of clear that
these people were were going places. All
right. Um so Deepseek takes a very
different scaling strategy than uh mini
CPM and and several others in trying to
optimize their hyperparameters. Like
they're not going to really do MUP,
right? They're not going to do this like
interesting scaling adjustments. Um
instead they're going to directly try
going to try to fit a scaling law to
estimate both the optimal batch size and
the optimal learning rate right um so we
know that the learning rate and batch
sizes should actually change with scale
but if the way in which they change are
predictable just like a scaling law then
we're good to go right like we don't
really need to to worry about very much
um so what they do is they basically run
extensive grid searches at v at v
various different scales and they try to
find the optimum right so this is an
example of the kind of thing they're
doing. You know, they're sweeping
learning rates, they're sweeping batch
sizes, and they're looking at sort of
the terminal loss uh if they're
processing a particular number of
tokens, right? So, they fix the compute
and then they vary these two. Um they'll
do this across several different scales
and then they'll basically try to
identify what the lowest loss is. So, in
this case, the lightest color, right?
So, they'll put a little star there. Um
and then they'll do this across scales.
So if you do you know this across
sufficiently many scales you will get a
plot that looks like this right and this
plot is saying okay um I'm going to vary
uh my non-mbbedding trading flops across
some range and you can kind of see these
gray dots over here right um and I'm
going to vary as I vary this my optimal
batch size will change where remember
the optimal batch size is derived by
looking at these big grids and and kind
of finding the minimizer right um and I
will get something that kind of looks
like a line, right? The optimal backside
should scale with my non-mbedding flops.
And similarly for my optimal learning
rate, right, I'll get a bunch of gray
dots um in my sort of non-mbbedding
flops range. Um and then I can fit a
line to that to try to estimate what my
optimal learning rate should look like,
right? Um so this is fairly nice. Um and
I guess one thing I'll point out is, you
know, their their uh full runs are on
the star, right? These are the runs that
they chose um at higher flops. They they
have much higher batch sizes and much
lower learning rates, right? The stars
are the things they actually ran for
their their big runs. Um these fits look
reasonable for the batches, right? This
kind of does look like a line. The one
on the learning rate. I'm not quite sure
that constitutes, you know, the best
linear fits that I've seen in my life.
Um but I guess it works, so it's
probably fine, right? like the models do
train, the models do get reasonable
things. Um I think this is the one I
would say like drawback of the learning
rates approach. It's not really clear
that if you try to do this grid search
kind of thing, unless your grid is in
the right place, you've got a lot of
quantization error and then you're not
getting very good uh scaling law fits
and you end up with kind of something
that looks like an arbitrary linear
thing going on.
Okay. Oh yeah, sorry.
How come for the same number of training
flops there you get multiple data points
with a large range of optimal learning
rates?
>> Why is it that you get a large range of
optimal learning rates for different
training flops? Is that is that the
question on the y axis over here?
>> Yeah. Um so the reason I think there is
because of the the changes to uh the
model sizes and things like this.
Um and so you know 2024 was back in the
era where I think every open model
builder was replicating the entire
scaling law stack and so you know
deepseek also complements um the you
know like like learning rate analysis
with uh basically a chinchilla
replication. Um and to do that they're
also going to do the same thing as mini
CPM. They're going to follow the WSD
style learning rate. um they have a
weird little variation where they do two
decay phases instead of one. I am not
really sure why this is. Um it hasn't
really been a thing that has taken off
afterwards, but it is a thing that they
do. Regardless, the whole point here is
to say WSD is an effective approach and
you can use that to replicate
Chinchilla. Um and Deepseek, you know,
has much nicer scaling curves. Um the
mini CPM because of their choice to go
with isoflop. So they get these very
nice, you know, clean sweeps. um across
the the fixed flops ranges and then they
also get fairly nice and clean uh
chinchilla style trade-offs um as
before. So this allows them to
essentially replicate the chinchilla
results um and get you know a similar
kind of of a data model scaling law.
Really the point that I'm showing with
this is just to say look the chinchilla
laws have been replicated by other
people at largeish compute ranges. Um so
that analysis is generally sound. Um,
finally, I think, you know, this is kind
of the I'm a little bit sad that these
kinds of plots are now somewhat rare in
open source release papers, but you
know, this is really the the final
punchline of a lot of scaling law work,
right? You train a bunch of small
curated models, you know, at smaller uh
compute ranges and then you kind of like
draw out the power law and then in the
end you get something pretty close to
reality if you scale out enough, right?
So, the two stars are the models that
they actually trained. The gray dots are
their scaling law fits. um and they're
getting like pretty good predictions on
their star. I mean, it could be better,
but it's not bad at all. And so they're
able to get some pretty accurate scaling
law predictions um on real, you know,
open source models that they've trained.
Okay, actually I'll stop here. Um if
people have questions about the DeepSeek
stuff, um feel free to ask them. I think
my oneline summary here is to say, you
know, this is the other approach to
dealing with the sensitive
hyperparameters. You can either attempt
to stabilize them or you can attempt to
just scaling law fit them, right? And
then just go with the scaling law and
deepse represents the more like fit the
scaling law approach to this problem.
Good. Okay. Um so there are other models
um more recent ones that have you know
nice scaling laws that they talk about.
Um, as I said before though, I think a
lot of this work is now, you know, kind
of what's the it's kind of like all
known to everybody and so no one is
really putting a lot of this stuff into
like big sections into the paper. So if
you look at Quen 2.5, they say something
like okay well we need to tune some
optimal hyperparameters like batch sizes
and learning rates. So we do a bunch of
scaling experiments to figure out what
the optimum are and then we have a
scaling law and we predict the optimum
and then we're able to do that even
forees. Right? So this is basically the
same thing as the deepseek analysis,
right, that they're talking about in
quen 2.5. Um same thing with quen 3,
right? By the time it's quen 3, you
know, they say, "All right, we've
already figured out what to do in quen
2.5. We're just doing exactly the same
thing, right?" So this has become part
of a very standard recipe um that you
use in order to nail down the optimum
optimal learning rates and batches.
Um
Kim K2 um is probably the newest paper
that I'll talk about of the series. Um
at this point I'm just going to quickly
go through several papers mainly to give
you sort of um a overview of what people
are doing in terms of scaling work in
the in the open source model releases.
Um so Kimmy K2 and a few others um have
focused on essentially scaling laws. So
you know it's 2026 most people know you
know how to do a chinchilla scaling law
or even a learning rate scaling law.
What things are new? Well, a lot of
these companies are now switching to
fully switching toes, right? And if
you're doing that, you really want to
know, you know, am I training the right
amount of active parameters? And so
they're doing things like, okay, we're
going to vary the flops and look at my
losses and I'm going to do so for
different levels of sparity so that I
can figure out how much sparity helps or
hurts my losses. And their conclusion of
course is as if you look at the
different sparsity levels, the more
sparse your network, right, the better
your validation loss given a flop.
Unsurprising. But now the fact that they
can quantitatively know what the
relationship is between sparity and loss
means that they can make sort of more
rational decisions about, you know, how
much sparity to put into their model.
And they they look at this and they say,
"Okay, what we're going to do is we're
going to use a sparity of 48 because at
that point we're hitting diminishing
returns on our scaling loss, right?" Um
so you can kind of see how this kind of
analysis is used to justify different
architectural decisions uh across
different open source releases. um Hunan
which is another uh open- source uh from
a few years ago now um they do a very
similar thing right like I think every
company once they switch to thee has to
do this kind of like uh scaling law to
figure out how the number of activated
parameters or the amount of sparsity
changes training loss and then they kind
of redo a lot of these analyses so for
example in in Hungan's case they end up
with like a 96 data point per active
parameter ratio in their case they're
fixing the sparsity level and so that's
not a thing that they're searching over.
Um, llama 3 also has some nice scaling
loss. Um, unfortunately
they're not particularly useful ones.
Um, they do isoflop style scaling and
and get slightly different but similar
ratios for token to model. Um the most
interesting thing that they do in terms
of scaling in uh llama 3 is the the plot
on the right here which is you know they
have the usual scaling law which is the
left panel that's saying if I have more
compute then the log prob on the the
sort of answer for a benchmark um sort
of decays consistently and on the right
side they show okay well you know if you
have better sort of log loss then the
downstream accuracy also goes up right
so they're basically saying well we can
fit a sigmoid on these purple points and
that might give us a sense of like how
good these different models are. Um you
can kind of see there's systematic
deviations from the curve. So I don't
really know if I would really buy that
this curve is like the one truth that's
going on. But you can certainly see that
it is consistent with a sigmoidal
scaling um mapping from the loss to the
accuracy which I think is very useful
right because we've been talking only
about kind of log losses but there is a
tight coupling in some cases or in many
cases between log losses and downstream
accuracy.
Okay. Um and then sort of for one last
um uh paper that I want to talk about
for scaling, minimax 01 uh from last
year had this nice set of scaling
experiments where they were doing the
exact kind of thing I was saying um is a
useful affordance of scaling from two
lectures a um architecture variations.
And so they wanted to understand okay I
have lightning attention which is like
some kind of linear attention
architecture. I have a softmax version
like full attention and I have a hybrid
version that mixes the two. How do these
things scale you know is it the case
that if I scale up one of them will get
much worse than the other. Um and so you
know you can kind of see um this they're
replicating essentially the Kaplan plots
of like as I increase uh flops you know
how do the learning curves change and
you know is the number of parameters
that I need different for different
levels of compute for these different
architectures and the answer is for the
most part kind of no that you know
hybrid and lightning and softmax are all
comparable for the most part and they
require similar model sizes and this set
of plots is used to justify their use of
the hybrid architecture in the actual
deploy system. Right? So this is exactly
the kind of decision-m that you would do
based upon a scaling law. Okay? So
that's basically what I wanted to cover
for the the recent scaling law recipes
from the various companies. Um so the
two things as I said before for the
deepseek recipe right the key thing is
the scaling analysis on the batch and
learning rate. This is the scaling based
approach. Um and mini CPM follows a more
of a MUP style approach to to try to get
invariances. Um and then you know we see
some trends. We see that like Kimmy and
Quen and others are do or and Hunan are
doing these like scaling experiments as
they switch to. We see some architecture
work by Miniax. Um and we also see you
know some isoflops analysis being
replicated uh by several others. Um and
the to return to a previous point right
the point here is I think a lot of
companies are now less detailed because
the core scaling machinery like you know
doing chinchilla or doing learning rate
scaling is now fairly well understood by
everybody. So there's no necessarily uh
val extra value in you know showing
those experiments for some of these
releases or at least that's my guess for
why we have much fewer of these kinds of
experiments in the release. Okay. Um,
I'll take one minute and then sort of
pause and let you digest and ask a
question or two uh in case you have
questions for this part.
>> Oh yeah.
>> So all these uh cover the the
pre-training stage. So my question is uh
what changes and what do not change when
uh now post training is kind of
standardized process for model
developing.
>> Yeah. So the question was about um what
hap what changes about this when you do
or when you think about post- training I
guess broadly um I think that's still a
big open question. Um there's no great
way to do like fully integrated scaling
with like post- training accounted for
because post- training like can
sometimes really change the nature of
like you know what pre-training you
should do. Um, the closest things that I
can think of to thinking about
post-training is there's been some work
on like understanding like coverage or
like you know uh diversity notions in
pre-training that would help predict
what happens in post- training but it's
still pretty nent work. I don't think
there's any good answer to the question
of like what do we do about you know
synergy with post- trainining.
Cool. Okay.
So now we're going to talk about the
other piece. Um so I think the two
remaining parts of this lecture um kind
of map on cleanly to the two examples.
So uh I'm going to talk about one
approach, one set of approaches which is
about scaling laws for learning rates,
batch sizes and optimizers, right? That
kind of corresponds to the to the
deepseek approach to the world. Um and
then I'm going to talk about kind of the
MUP stuff, right? Like the that's kind
of the mini CPM approach to the world.
Can we just reparameterize everything to
make it so that we don't have to worry
about scale? So, we're going to now talk
about kind of the deepseek approach. Um,
how do we scale learning rate properly?
Um, and so there's going to be a
hyperparameter part and a optimizer
choice part. Um, and I'm going to draw
quite a bit from this pretty recent
preprint um from the step fund folks
folks. Um I don't think there's like a
great you know really truly like
reliable robust uh study on
hyperparameters um especially learning
rates um but this is probably getting
somewhat close the stepfund folks train
you know credible large models and
release them and they burned a ton of
compute in grid searching the space of
hyperparameters in this scaling law
study. So I'll go through this and like
you know show you some intriguing
empirical phenomena about how learning
rates, batch size and all those affect
downstream losses.
Okay. Um so lots of people have talked
about lots of different ways of scaling
learning rate and batch sizes as roughly
as a function of compute. Um and you
know the Stefon survey not survey paper
the hyperparameter tuning paper has this
very nice table that like captures a lot
of this. Um, and I'll point out a couple
of different things. Um, some of this we
already know. So the very top row, this
open AAI scaling law, this is from
Kaplan. Uh, if you look at the batch
size over there, notice how it says like
2 E18, you know, capital L to the
exponent. That's critical batch sizes,
right? It's basically saying, you know,
you should scale your batch size as a
function of your terminal loss. Great.
Right. Um, deepseek we just saw, right?
This is kind of the the um compute-based
scaling loss for both learning rate and
batch size. Um and there's been a couple
of other folks that have proposed
various kinds of scaling um including
mini CPM which we've talked about as
well. Um another important thing that I
want to point out is that these you know
formulas for learning rate and batch
sizes they don't even have the same
inputs right like people don't even seem
to agree what are the variables that
should affect these learning rates. like
you know the OpenAI one is terminal loss
whereas the the step fun folks uh they
claim that the right batch size scaling
is a function of the data right so
there's a lot of different sort of
disagreements about the nature of
scaling for hyperparameters
um and I think one thing I'll say as I
go through this is not to take even this
last row as kind of gospel right a lot
of these things are are pretty brittle
in many ways but the experiments and the
phenomena are things that you can learn
well from so I'll do that. Um, so the
design of this paper is very similar to
the deepseek one. Like they're just
going to train a ton of models to, you
know, grid out both the learning rate
space and the batch size space and do
them across a range of models and range
of uh data set sizes. And by doing so,
they they hope to essentially saturate
the hyperparameter space for a set of
small models and then nail down um what
the optimum is. And much like in the
Deepseek design, they're going to be,
you know, after they grid up the space,
you know, in this case, they have a
contour plot, but the underlying objects
are just they run a bunch of models, um,
they aim to try to minimize sort of the
losses, right? And the contour plots are
quite nice. I feel like they give a good
visualization.
um they ran a pretty high resolution
grid and thanks to that one of the
things that we can see is that they can
actually plot out a fairly high
resolution contour of what the
hyperparameter space looks like. In this
case, this is a slice at um 1B
parameters and 100B tokens I believe. Um
and you can sort of see on the right
side that surface is the hyperparameter
sort of landscape you know as a function
of the batch size which is kind of you
on one axis and learning rate which is
the other axis. How does the loss change
if you fix um the total amount of data
in the model? Now, you know, we see that
each slice like if you fix a batch size
or you fix a learning rate, right? Each
slice is kind of nice and convex and
it's almost even smooth. Um and this is
quite nice because it means that you
can, you know, kind of search for the
optimal hyperparameter, you know, fairly
nicely and you can be confident that the
minima is not too far off. This was very
jaggedy. you might have some you know
very serious doubts about whether this
kind of program of gritting the space is
even viable. Um also this should maybe
give you some nice intuition about the
smoothness of the hyperparameter space
in general. Um and I think there's
actually one really interesting general
scaling trend um and looking at other
related papers to this topic I think I
don't know if I've seen any
contradicting evidence to this uh
observation.
So I think the one thing that seems very
interesting and one of the key takeaways
of this work is essentially if you're
looking at the optimal batch size,
right? The only thing that seems to
depend on is the total amount of data
that you're training on. Um so this
right hand plot is the is the one to
look at, right? So x-axis here is the
amount of data that you're training on.
The different colored dots, those are
different models. Notice how you know
the different colored dots seem to
follow roughly the same trend line here.
Um fairly predictable one. Um and this
is in log log scale. So you you should
expect some sort of a power law as a
function of D, right? Um on the left
panel we have uh the dependence of
learning rate. And we see that this is a
very different behavior, right? Bigger
models, so if you go from blue all the
way to this pink color, right? Bigger
models have uh smaller optimal learning
rate and larger amounts of data have
higher optimal uh learning rate, which
is kind of counterintuitive actually.
Um and so this might be a little
fragile. There are other kinds of papers
that argue that the dependence on D
should be kind of reversed. Um but the
trends here at least on this experiment
are quite clear.
Okay. Um and you know uh one final thing
that I kind of want to point out is the
learning rates are actually pretty
robust and I think this is backed up by
a lot of experiences and experiments
that people have. You know, I think
people have a sense of like, you know,
actually as a poll, like do people know
what a good like hyperparameter is? Like
if you were told to train a language
model tomorrow, like would it be 1G -3,
1 EG4, right? I feel like we roughly
have a sense of like actually this range
of hyperparameters for learning rates is
generally a good starting point. Um, and
that is generally true. So, so the
scaling loss that they got, um, you
know, actually transfer over to, for
example, to a to a certain extent. Um
the yellow stars which might be a little
harder to see are the predictions from
their scaling loss. The red X's are sort
of the optima that are derived uh sort
of directly on the so you know you
switch to ane um you don't end up with a
very different scaling model as long as
you're you're roughly controlling for
for active uh parameters. Um the one
thing that does seem a little bit more
you know potentially dicey is you know
as you shift the training data the
optimal learning rates and the optimal
batch sizes do shift a little bit right
which means that all of these phenomena
are likely contingent like the specific
numbers that are are in these scaling
models and so on um are potentially
contingent to the data that you train on
um more so than others. And so uh I want
to flash this back up um you know before
I sort of move on. Right? So you end up
with some sort of simple scaling law at
the end which says okay batch size you
know maybe should be roughly square root
of the number of data times some
constant your learning rate should kind
of scale you know upwards with batch or
upwards with data but downwards um with
the model size um and that's kind of a
surprising effect um but you know not
maybe crazy because these experiments
often in many cases are assuming like
chinchilla like scaling in which case
you know those two would kind of cancel
and as increase compute your learning
rate should go down right hopefully that
chinchilla comment was clear what I mean
is when you're scaling by chinchilla um
n and d are sort of both driven by
compute and as compute goes up you
expect your learning rate to go down
right and so you will end up with
something like the deepse law claw where
the learning rate decreases with compute
and the batch size increases with
compute albeit with different exponents
um than the deepse claw
cool
okay um so in some sense this is like
the the newest and most largecale
version of the deepseek analysis. And
this is one way that you know if you
were doing the scaling loss style
approach, you would approach this
problem of fitting um a learning rate.
Okay. Um so you know that's the
hyperparameter story. If someone has
questions feel free to stop me. Um and
then next right after I'm going to move
on to talking about optimizers. I think
this is one thing that I you know didn't
have time to talk about in the in the
architectures uh lecture that was
already a pretty packed lecture um but I
think it it would be sort of a
disservice to you if I don't talk about
optimizers and optimizers are scale
dependent so this is a good place to put
them and talk about some of the latest
and greatest developments in optimizers
and their relationship with scale
>> oh yeah
>> um so I guess like I'm trying to figure
out how to interpret this like does that
mean we should just take the scaling
laws that we have and then apply them
rather than running our own search.
>> Yeah. I mean I think it depends like
what regime you're in. The question is
like oh sorry to repeat it for the
online folks right is you know should we
just take the scaling law and run them
or like should we just do our own grit
search. Um you know it does kind of
depend on the amount of compute budget
that you have and how much you need to
nail it. Um I do think for example you
know maybe the step fun uh law if you're
in the right compute regime like close
to where they were running the grid
these are probably really good defaults
right like I would bet o on these over
like something I pull out my hat that
said you know if you were doing your own
big pre-training run um you are probably
going to have minor differences right
like you know someone might say I really
believe we should have a big weight
decay my architecture has a big weight
decay you know we don't know necessarily
that those things are going to scale the
same right um and So you might want to
actually redo a lot of this. And this is
why I think a lot of the, you know, the
the reports I showed you were redoing
chinchilla, redoing all these things
because there's enough minor differences
that people want to check and make sure
that they're like roughly first order
correct um with these results. Um I
think this will come up again in this
next optimizer part and I was talking
about this with earlier which is you
know scaling laws kind of have this very
scientific feel to them. It's like, oh
yes, fit these lines and extrapolate
them. But ultimately, a big part of
scaling laws is still vibes, right? It's
like, do I really believe that the
experiment setting of this step one
survey is similar enough to mine that
they will transfer? We can't possibly
know, right? There are always tiny
differences.
Good. Okay. So, now I get to talk about
optimizers. And I think there's been
some really exciting developments in LM
optimizers and maybe even deep learning
optimizers in general over the past year
or two. And so this is a exciting time
to talk about them. Um and so kind of
the story that I want to start with and
and one that like should maybe motivate
this subsection um is this comparison
over here or maybe we'll start on this
left panel. Right? So this is from um
nano GPBT speedrun which you know
inspired our assignment one and there
you know you have a really teenytiny
model that you're training on a fairly
short amount of time and you want to get
to I forget 3 point some loss as quickly
as possible right um and you know many
people have been hill climbing on this
benchmark and I think one of the more
you know remarkable things that have
happened on the benchmark is as a
benchmark called muon in in purple over
here came and you know got really
significant gains
over atom which is blue. It's right
underneath the green line over there.
So, you know, you can just look at the
green and the purple and that gap and
you say, "Wow, you know, lots of big
gains from just changing the optimizer
to this muon thing." Um, and it's not
even slower than atom, much slower than
Adam. That's great, right? Um, but then,
you know, there's a question of like,
well, is this thing actually good at
scale? Um, and then you go and run some
like scaling studies and maybe they're
not quite as good. You know, this is a
really tricky and important part of how
we do research, right? We have a small
scale experiment. We have something
that's scale dependent for sure, like an
optimizer. Um, and then we see really
big gains in the small scale. What do we
do about the large scale? Um, and more
than providing like a solid concrete
prescription. I I want us to maybe
almost even provide a story here so that
you can kind of get a sense of like what
we can do and what things we can't
necessarily know. Okay. Um, so actually
before I move on to the next slide, you
know, and and this kind of thing happens
all the time where you like come up with
a great thing small scale and it just
doesn't maybe pan out large scale. So
what's the difference? Um, I'm going to
spend a few slides talking about um,
Caillou and uh, and sort of Tenyu and
Percy and David's paper um, on basically
doing a large scale set of experiments
on comparing optimizers and do trying to
do that comparison better. I mean
there's a lot to learn about scaling and
other things from that but also just
standard deep learning stuff. Um you
know there's really basic things like
you know the hyperparameters for
different models are different. So if
you're scaling things up maybe they even
have different scaling exponents. So you
have to tune atom really well. So if you
tune it badly you know you get this this
darker brown line and you're like wow
this thing is much worse than all these
other algorithms that I have over here
on the left. But then you you change the
learning rate a little bit and you're
like, "Wow, actually all my gains went
away." Um, similarly on the right, you
know, you can have cases where maybe
you've tuned your learning rate well,
but now you've got other stuff like
weight decay that is not optimally
tuned. And so if you use the same weight
decay, then you're certainly going to
get a much worse result for this green
line, right? If you pick this, you know,
small weight decay, you'll get a much
worse result for this green line um than
if you pick the optimal weight decay,
right? So there's all sorts of like
pretty tricky things going on.
technically not a scaling thing but a
very important you know general
empirical machine learning thing that I
want to point out.
Um but maybe more relevant to the
discussion um in this class right now is
the scale dependence of these things.
And I think this is a good sort of case
study and example of how to really think
about algorithm development as a
function of scale because to me you know
there are two variables that are always
important when thinking about scale and
this paper exposes to some to most
extent like both of them. Um so one axis
is compute and you know if you're fixing
the compute oh sorry if you're fixing
the model size to data ratio like the
two are coupled together then this is
essentially a compute axis on the x-axis
here right so you always want to you
know whenever you're doing a study you
know essentially scale up the compute
and look at the trends as a function of
uh of scale and we see right here that
if we look at the relative speed up
between uh atom which is at 1.0 know by
definition and all these other
alternatives we see that you know muon's
really good at small scale and that gain
sort of diminishing down diminishes down
as we increase in scale that's that's
not really necessarily um the picture
that you want to see um there's another
axis that you should always be vigilant
of if you're doing algorithm development
and the other one that you should be
vigilant of is the chinchilla ratio so
the chinchilla ratio can be thought of
uh it is the ratio between you know how
much data you have and the amount of
model you have right and this is a
really really really important parameter
because some algorithms work well in
kind of the overp parameterized case
where you have a way bigger model than
you have lots of data, right? Maybe your
your algorithm adds some implicit
regularization, right? Or maybe it, you
know, is data inefficient but it works
well because of compute reasons, right?
So, you know, some algorithms might work
well at the small chinchilla ratio case.
Uh, in contrast, you know, other
algorithms might work well in the large
chinchilla ratio case where you have
lots of data per um per uh unit
parameter, right? because you can pack
knowledge more efficiently into the
parameters. Right? So this is a big big
big confounder. Even papers that I think
have pretty good hygiene in doing
scaling experiments on the model size
axis often uh neglect to or just don't
have the compute to sort of study the
chinchilla sort of token to to parameter
ratio. And this turns out to be
surprisingly important a lot of time in
this case it's not. In this case you
know you see that um the optimizer sort
of gains are pretty consistent. the
ratios between all the lines are the
same at different chinchilla ratios but
this is not always the case you always
want to be vigilant about both of these
scaling factors that's quite important
and then I'm going to you know also
point out you know if you have a new
algorithm or a new setting right um
establishing scaling is quite
non-trivial right so um I've taken this
from uh one of uh Will Held who was
working with Marin which was you know
Percy's open- source language model
training project um and there you know
they were basically trying to prove out
a particular set of hyperparameters this
isn't even like a new algorithm so this
is cautious atom C which is like a atom
variant um square root batch size
scaling and and a bunch of other sort of
standard looking things and you know
they're doing essentially the same sort
of chinchilla analysis that you've seen
all the other papers do um but because
this is not necessarily a paper this is
a bunch of you know people doing
experiments you don't just publish the
the successful one you know they have
the niceness of publishing their failed
runs um and The example here is that
they're doing basically standard
chinchilla stuff and it's looking great.
If you if you go up to this dashed
vertical line at 10 to the 20 something,
you know, this is a this is a really
beautiful looking scaling law to here
and then you know as you scale up it's
like well it gets a little bit worse,
it's a lot worse and then wow now that
run is not so good anymore, right? So
it's totally blown up on you. Um and the
point here is that you know even
good-looking scaling trends for many
orders of magnitude can suddenly kind of
bite you, right? right? Like it can
deviate from linear and then it can then
you know kind of blow up immediately.
And in their case you know the the fix
here is just picking more careful MUP
style parameterizations. Um optimizer
changes they switch to a pretty a
different kind of optimizer and you know
they get nicer scaling across orders of
magnitude. But the point here is to say
you know when I go back here and I say
okay well you should all do scaling
experiments you should scale all your
learning rates and so on. Um that's not
easy right? you end up in fairly
non-trivial fraction of the time with
plots that look like this. Um, and it's
all kind of horrible and you're not
quite sure what has gone wrong. Um,
good. Okay.
And then so the last thing um I want to
end with is just talking a little bit
about muon and sort of, you know, the
closing up out the mu muon story. Um,
so, you know, I feel like I have to talk
about muon in a little bit more detail
than I already have. um just because
it's beginning to be uh integrated into
large scale model training runs. Um
that's kind of the inclusion criteria
for a lot of you know new research
topics for the class you know has it
been in a big training run and muon now
checks that mark um and it's also just
kind of an interesting algorithm so I'll
mention it uh and talk about it for a
few minutes and then move on. So in
gradient descent we usually have a
fairly simple thing that's happening.
ignore line four for the m or sorry line
uh five for the moment and then you're
going to get roughly a standard you know
uh momentum based optimizer right I take
a gradient I uh add it to b of t this is
my momentum step right so I I continue
my momentum from before with parameter
mu and then I update my parameters based
on this momentum gradient very standard
you know momentum gradient stuff but
then I think the really interesting and
to me at least a bit of an out ofthe-box
set of ideas is to say well you know
gradients have this property that they
treat all the parameters are the same
but we know that not all the parameters
in a a language model or even a deep
neural network are the same some
parameters are like vector parameters
like they belong to the RMS norm some
parameters are matrix parameters like
for the attention or for MLPS right and
matrix parameters are probably different
than vector parameters and so that's
kind of the starting point for this idea
and I think a really interesting one um
and so the one thing that you could do
about matrix parameters is you can start
to look at their spectra, right? Like
they are matrices. Matrices have igen
values and singular values. And so you
can do things to the singular values.
And so um what you do here in in muon is
this fairly simple idea. You compute a
gradient. You take a momentum step and
now I take my update B of T and instead
of directly applying it to my parameters
in line six, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to do this Newton Schultz thing,
Newton Schultz 5 to be specific. Um, and
what that is is it's going to
orthogonalize the B of T matrix. Um, and
so I've written the operation down there
on the bottom. You know, let's say I
take B of T. I write it as singular
value decomposition. Uspose.
And then I make all of my singular
values one, right? So if my singular
values are really big, I'll shrink them
back to unit. If they're really small,
I'll expand them back up to being unit.
And then I take UV transpose. And that's
my new update that I'm going to apply.
Right? Um if you want intuition for this
and you already have intuition for
something like adrad or these other or
atom even um in adrad or atom you're
going to divide by kind of the size of
the gradient right? So every coordinate
is roughly going to be the same size. Um
in muon you are operating in the
spectral norm instead. So every kind of
direction is going to be unit size.
Right? And notice that this only makes
sense for a matrix. I can only define
this notion of a of a singular value
decomposition for a matrix valued B of
P. Right? So um the interesting thing
about muon is it's a matrix optimizer.
So you apply it to these matrix valued
parameters. And for the vector valued
ones, you know, you might still use
something like atom W, right? Because
those don't really have any sort of
interaction with the Newton Schultz
term. Oh, also Newton Schultz is a is a
approximation to that operation that
only uses matrix multiplies, right? So
it's systems efficient and not exactly
the the orthogonalization. Um but okay
like why have I spent you know all this
time talking about muon? Well first of
all it's very you know um powerful for
things like the nano GPD speedrun. It
was discovered for this you know set of
things. Um and so you might think that
it works well. As I said in the previous
slide you know there have been some
scaling studies that have argued that
the gain for muon sort of decreases uh
as scale goes up. But then, you know, I
kind of want to close off this story,
which, you know, I think initially this
came out and I was like, "Wow, muon's
kind of interesting. I wonder if anyone
will scale it up." And then Caillou and
other others scaled up Muan and they
said, "Well, maybe it doesn't work super
well." Um, and I thought the story was
kind of closed here. I was like, "Well,
maybe this is done. Uh, no one will
spend the big compute to to scale this
guy up to the full pre-training size."
And then Kimmy K2 comes out um and that
whole model is trained with muon. um
like fully with muon with a few bells
and whistles to prevent muon from like
blowing up on you. They found a whole
bunch of instability issues. Um but
Kimmy K2 is an outstandingly good model,
right? It's a very good model. Um and
the training curves look, you know,
reasonable. Um and so really what this
suggests is like well, you know, muon
worked at scale like is it better than
atom? Kimmy K2 certainly doesn't have
any ablation. So we don't know at that
scale, but it is certainly a valid and
workable solution. Um and so what's the
point of this story? It's to say it's
really hard to know whether something
works at scale. It's very very hard. Um
but thus far a lot of like smallcale
experiments and transferring them up to
large scale has been the way by which we
do science, right? And so you know you
still want to respect things like the
nano GPT speedrun. We learn quite a bit
from that and get good ideas and then
eventually they make their way to the
big models. We'll see if you know people
continue to do ablations at big scale
and really nail down you know is muon
better than atomw at scale and so on.
Those are interesting questions to which
we don't yet have the answers.
Okay. Um I'll pause here for a moment.
This is the end of my optimizer section.
I want to make sure everyone's good also
especially because I I was talking about
muon and that's a whole new can of worms
that I haven't talked about much before.
>> Yeah. Is the organization
faster on GPU?
>> Great. Yeah. The question was is the SVD
fast on GPUs? SVD is not fast on GPUs,
but they're not doing SVD. What they're
doing is Newton Schultz. Newton Schultz
is a matrix multiply only finite
iteration algorithm that approximates
the process of orthogonalizing a matrix.
Um, so there's like kind of several
clever pieces here. One of them is kind
of the idea of like treating it as a
matrix on its own. And then there's this
orthogonalization idea. And then there's
the systems piece of doing it with
Newton Schultz. So those are all like
important interesting pieces. Yeah. Back
there.
>> Uh are the hyperpounders shared? No,
they're they're different. Yeah. Um I
think you know there are several people
that uh have been working on this like
muon style line of work. Um and one of
them I think like Jeremy Bernstein you
know I think he he's been saying like
actually like every layer should have
its own learning rate. You know I think
the the ultimate limit of this is like
you know you go from or even sorry like
every layer should have its own
optimizer right um the ultimate limit of
this is to say every parameter in a
transformer is different why not have a
different optimizer for each one of them
right and so you would have to tune
hyperparameters for each one of them as
well which I do not want to do but you
know that's maybe the future of of
optimization yes
>> what's
the like for on the learning rate and
batch size like they just consider like
these two things and then you pick the
best out of those and then you kind of
present the two other things but do
these things like interact with each
other.
>> Yeah. Or for or maybe the the version of
the question that I interpreted was you
know a lot of these people are just
tuning learning rate in batch slides and
do they do this on the grid but
presumably these things interact with a
whole bunch of other hyperparameters
aren't you worried about that and I
think in general yes you are worried
about hyperparameter interactions but
realistically they grow they grow
exponentially right like this is not a
thing where you can grid out the whole
space um and so I think the the thing
that people often do is they grid the
stuff that's most concerning and most
sensitive and learning rates are very
important. I think if you've you know
ever tuned stuff, learning rates are the
most important thing to tune. So they
very aggressively go on that and then
stuff like weight decay they might do a
univariate sweep afterwards right to to
be locally optimal with respect to those
parameters.
Good. Okay.
All right. So the final part of this
lecture is I want to talk about MUP. Um,
MUP is a bit of a mysterious object even
with many papers written about it and
sort of in fact even many
implementations. Um, I don't think all
of them even agree on what the
underlying math is or what the
underlying implementation should be. Um,
but there's a core set of ideas that are
shared and it does seem generally
effective and so I'll talk about my
interpretation of the whole program
let's call it. Um, so the goal hopefully
is very clear and I think this picture
is the goal. The picture being well if
we increase the size of our model in
this case just width our optimal
learning rate normally shifts but
ideally we want the optimal learning
rate to be the same no matter what right
that is the game that we would like to
play and the knobs that I'm willing to
tune to do this is I'm willing to mess
with the initializations at a per layer
basis I'm willing to mess with the
learning rates on a per parameter basis
as well um and then I'm sometimes
willing to scale up or down things like
residual connections right based on the
size of my model. Okay, so that's the
game that I'd like to play. Um, and how
well does it work in practice? There's
been several papers that have studied
these fairly extensively. Um, Cerebrris
Cerebrris, which is really a chip
company. Um, also has a language model
training arm. Um, run by Hessnes of the
Scaling Law, you know, paper fame. Um,
and they actually I feel like they do
very interesting things because they now
are writing lots of papers about MUP
scaling of language models. Um and they
have cerebrus GPT uh from a couple years
ago where they were training you know
the 0.1 to 13B models using the usual
chinchilla recipe but also including a
MUP variant which they use to try to to
tune the hyperparameters more
effectively. Um and I think one of the
the nice things about this is they find
that you know if they use the MUP
parameterization
um then their scaling law fits are
generally more stable. Their their
projected MUP trends are you know almost
right on the money for their actual
models whereas I think their their non-
muup models sort of fluctuated much more
wildly in terms of the loss predictions
um that they had. And so their claim was
okay is maybe a really good idea. So
this is validated at scale. you saw mini
CPM and others. Um, many people have
trained models with MUP variants. Um, so
I could also talk a lot about, you know,
training or examples of models trained
with MUP. But I think maybe the more
interesting thing for me to do right now
is actually to talk about the conceptual
foundations and the math sort of um for
MUP. And if you're interested in this
and you want to read a somewhat
accessible paper, I would recommend this
one. This is the paper that I think for
me was the clearest. Um there are
several papers. Greg Yang who who kind
of started this research program has a
series of papers called tensor programs.
I find them somewhat inscrutable. Um
Jeremy Bernstein you know who was also
working on the muon stuff has written
this nice sort of re not recap paper
like a like a review paper sort of
putting it into a different framework
which I think is very accessible. Um and
there's several others by physicists
that are also um interesting in terms of
explaining what MUP is. the cerebrous
people actually do a bit of that as
well. Okay, but anyway, returning to
this paper, um the core idea of MUP is
based off of two kind of assertions,
right? And this is a very physicist way
of thinking about this. So, if I make my
network big, let's say I'm only changing
the width for now, right? I'm making the
width of my network big. Um I'm going to
assert two invariants that should hold
as I do the scaling limit. First of all,
um the activations at initialization. So
if I initialize my model and I put in
some random data, the activations should
remain the same size roughly as a
function of the network. Right? So if
they blow up with the network size or
they shrink to zero with the network
size, I've chosen a wrong
parameterization. And that kind of makes
sense, right? My activation should be
roughly the same scale um regardless of
the size of my network. Now after one
gradient step, um the change in my
activation should be O of one. Right? So
this is what people call feature
learning. So feature learning means if I
take a gradient step things in my
network change a significant amount and
that this amount should be a fixed
function of the width of the network. Um
in case you know some of you are
theorists right? You know you might be
familiar with neural tangent kernels
neural tangent kernels would have a very
different behavior. Those would be the
kinds of things where the change in
activations actually vanish as a
function of the of the network width and
you don't want that because you do want
the network to change and learn features
and do things even in the limit of your
big sort of neural networks. Okay, so
these two are the invariants. They kind
of make sense. They're basically saying
activations and the change in the
activations should remain roughly
similar as a function of the width of
the network. And then um note that I'm
gonna sometimes go back and forth
between individual activations which is
this and then the norm which you know if
each activation is roughly O of one the
norm of the whole vector or of
activation should be square root of the
number of hidden units in that layer.
Okay so that's the main thing. Now the
thing about mu is it's kind of
interesting because it starts with you
know this very uh simple and palatable
set of assumptions. You might all agree
that this is a reasonable thing to do.
And then we're going to make a um a
number of additional strong assumptions.
But then in the end, we're going to get
a very simple set of scaling rules that
drop out of this. Um so remember what we
want to do is we want to make sure that
the activations that in it are roughly
units. So what do we do? Well, if we
have a simple deep linear network and we
initialize all of our weights as a sigma
squared, you know, scaled gausian, um,
then what is going to be kind of the
spectral norm of this matrix? Well, you
can write that down, right? I'm not
going to ask you to verify that, but
that's, you know, standard matrix
concentration arguments for the operator
norm of a random gausian matrix. And
then now note that in you know certain
regimes where the fan out is I think not
much bigger than the fan in you're going
to get that the output of the layer is
kind of similar to the product of the
input of the layer times the operator
norm right this is always an upper bound
but this is you know approximate in
certain high dimensional regimes. Now if
this is true now what can we do? Well,
we can solve for sigma to try to keep
our activations the same across all the
layers and across all the width. So
imagine that at layer L minus one um I
have sort of square root of L minus one
activation and this is remember you know
consistent with this notation that you
know at least for this whole vector I
should have square root of N of L right
so this is our our base case for our
induction and then our inductive case
says well you know remember that I have
this operator norm at layer L which is
this function of the fan in and the fan
out and so this is going to be equal to
this if I pick a particular sigma So
let's say uh this is the ons I'm going
to assume that this is the answer and
then we'll see what happens to the
induction. If I pick this as a
hypothesis and I plug this into the
sigma notice that I get that the ratio
of the operator norm is this the ratio
of the fan out over the sorry square
root of the fan out over the square root
of the fan in. And then I plug this back
in here and then I'm going to get that
the norm of the output is going to be
equal to the square root of the number
of units in my layer plus some lower
order terms that I'm not going to bother
to keep track of. Right? So you know
where this sigma came out of I mean this
is you know drawing it out of a hat but
we can kind of verify that if I you know
plug this sort of noise initialization
into my formula then essentially at
every layer the size of my activations
is roughly equal to the square root of
the number of hidden units at that layer
right um there are some assumptions made
here like this approximate equals but
this is like mostly a legitimate uh set
of assumptions so condition A1's pretty
simple
Um, condition A2 is a little bit hairier
to be honest. Um, so really we need to
deal with the updates now and um, I'm
only going to consider the case of a
single example in a batch for SGD for a
linear neural network. So deep linear
network. Um, so what is this going to
look like? Well, the change in my uh,
weights for a particular layer L. um you
know if you think about how this is
going to behave it's going to be a rank
one update between my gradient for the
loss and sort of the activations right
this is true you know just because of
the behavior of the backwards right the
forwards is a rank one multiplication
the backwards is going to be a rank one
outer product um so now you know this is
the change in the weights and now what
is the change in the activations at that
layer well the change in the activations
you know I just take h= w * hl L minus
one and I expand this out right and I
expand this out into this formula. This
is going to be exactly the change in the
activation at layer L and it's going to
have two terms. One that is sort of the
direct term from changes in the
activation at L minus one and the cross
term in some sense of what happens
because my weights have changed not just
because the activations at the previous
layer have changed. Right? So there's
two terms to this uh to this update. And
so this is kind of the change in the
activation at layer L. And now what I'm
going to do is I'm going to look through
each of these three terms. I want each
of these three terms to have the same
order of magnitude. And I want that
order of magnitude to be square root of
n. Why is that? Remember that, you know,
if I go back two slides, the condition
that I want for A2 is that after one
gradient step, the change in activation
should be O of one or omega of one. And
so if I want that to be true, then the
norm of that layer should be square root
of N L. And so to do that, what I want
is for each of these three terms to be
to have that order of magnitude. And if
that's true and there's no
cancellations, um, then this, you know,
is going to be the right order of
magnitude. You can kind of see the
sketchy pieces adding up, right? We're
assuming things like no cancellations
and so on. But this is giving us some
interesting ways of thinking about the
magnitude of each of these objects. So
you know, at this point, you know, the
the right thing way to think about this
is not like, okay, Tatsu is sitting here
doing like rigorous mathematics. You
know what I am doing here is I'm
basically keeping track of all the
orders of magnitude of all the terms and
I am saying that given our assumptions
how big should these roughly be it's
like kind of physicist math. Um no
offense to physicists um this was
developed by physicists in this way.
Okay. Um
okay so now really oh sorry go back one
slide just to to make all this clear. Um
so the first term this comes by almost
assumption right it's kind of the
inductive assumption. We assume that
delta h of l minus one has the right
order of magnitude. Right? So this comes
for free. Um these other two terms,
these are trickier. We have these terms
that multiply um the change in my
weights in operator norm times square
roo<unk> of l minus one. And so because
these two are the sort of order of
magnitudes of both of these terms, we
kind of know how big this delt needs to
be, right? We can solve for this because
we know that this left hand side needs
to be square root nl. And then we have
this term. So we solve for this operator
norm and that's exactly this quantity.
Right? So so this is going to be the
goal for the next slide. I want to make
I want to try to figure out what kinds
of learning rates are going to give me
an update that's roughly scaled as the
square root of the fan out over the
square root of the fan in. Right? So
that's the goal right as I said after I
pick a learning rate this should roughly
be true. So how can we do that? Well,
we're going to make yet another
assumption, and this is probably the
least palatable of the assumptions in my
opinion, which is that we're going to
assume that the, you know, the loss
update is going to be scaled by unit. In
other words, you know, we're going to
assume that, you know, our model is
actually making some appreciable
non-trivial progress as a function of
scale and that that's roughly similar.
Not quite sure that's palatable to me,
but that is yet another assumption. So,
we throw that down. But now the the
point of this assumption is that if this
is true, the rest of the math works out
quite cleanly because the change in the
loss is you know the product of my
gradient plus how much my weights
change. This is tailor approximation.
And then because this is rank one I can
rewrite this thing as a probinius norm
and as an operator norm. Um and so this
right hand side now allows us to to get
what we want. This is O of one. This
term we want to be square root NL
over<unk> L minus one. That's this term
on the right here. And then finally I
have this gradient of L term. Um and
this is going to be square roo<unk> of N
L minus one over<unk> NL. And then so
now what ADA do I need? Well the ADA
that I need is going to be solving for
this quantity which is the ratio of
these two guys which is NL over NL minus
one. Right? So um we made this one
assumption that the left hand side of
this is O of one and then we've solved
for all the quantities and we've ended
up with a fan out over fanin ratio for a
learning rate for a layer. Um for one
side note that I'll make is that for
atom because of kind of the changes in
in some of this um you're going to get
like a 1 over NL minus one scaling which
I'll I'll mention here. Okay. Um so I've
walked through a bunch of kind of
hopefully intuitive looking scaling
arguments for various components. Um but
in the end maybe you are interested in
like what does this mean? What does this
do for me? Um what this means is that
we're going to change how we um set our
initializations and learning rates a
little bit. Um so our initialization is
going to look like so for mu the blue
box is kind of what we do. Our
initialization is going to be 1
over<unk> nl minus one times a component
that is 1 over the<unk> fan out over fan
in. So if this is one then this is
equivalent to the usual initialization.
This is the standard parameterization.
But if this ratio is not smaller than
one then you get basically something
different. You get something that's
closer to the square root fan out over
fan in. The learning rate normally you
would set to be a constant as a function
of your model size. But you would want
to set this to the ratio of fan out and
fan in. And maybe more interestingly for
Adam this whole thing is a little bit
more different. I'm not going to even
touch the derivation for that. um where
you drop this one over uh NL term and
you get one over the fan in as kind of
the layer specific learning rate. Um and
so basically layers that have big fanins
for atom get smaller learning rates. It
allows you to have these layer adaptive
learning rates that are quite
interesting. Okay. Um so that was kind
of the derivation of MUP. um maybe you
know I went through a lot of detail so I
do want to maybe talk about what the
highle point of that was and the highle
point of that is mup as sort of a
argument is very interesting not only is
there like actual useful stuff the way
in which you get to the algorithm is
itself interesting because it's this
very different kind of math in which
you're saying okay you know I'm going to
take a scaling limit of my network and
then I assert some invariance about my
network and then I'm going to make
additional assumptions and then I'm
going to try to figure out what the
constraints on my sort of
hyperparameters are and the constraints
essentially give you certain kinds of
scaling limits on your hyperparameters
as well. Right? So this is a general
principle for coming up with different
kinds of algorithms or hyperparameter
scalings I think which are probably very
different than what you're used to um in
CS or ML training. So okay that was the
MEP derivation. Um I want to close out
on the MEP part with just a few like
empirical things. Um there's an
interesting paper by independent
researcher um on basically stress
testing MUP in lots of different ways.
Um and MUP can be you know thought of as
a as a proceed procedure for tuning
hyperparameters. Um and so you know
depending on how you do things like you
know atom is going to have a certain
learning rate as a function of different
components of the network. So you have
an embedding parameter, attention
parameters, input output MLPS or softmax
linears. All of those are going to have
different kinds of scalings um under MUP
as well as um not MUP scaling rules. And
the interesting thing here is um that
particular paper you know replicated a
bunch of the MUP results for uh language
models trained at different scales. And
maybe unsurprisingly he found you know
almost the headline result from uh mini
CPM and others which is that if you get
the MUP right and you're only scaling
with in this case in a very controlled
way um you get exactly the learning rate
optimality and variance that you know
baseline MUP um or just looking at kind
of a variant of MUP that sort of tracks
projection biases for attention both of
those uh transfer very nicely. But then
you might ask, you know, basically
there's a lot of things in the real
world that MUP does not handle, right?
Like technically swigloo does not fit
into MUP. Neither does, you know, uh
initial variations initialization or RMS
norm or if you really mess with your
optimizer that'll mess that up too. Um
and so you might ask like which of these
like you know things that are not
allowed by the theory really break MUP.
And actually for the most part these
mostly work with MUP. But some of the
things that don't work is if you you
know learn the gain term in RMS norm. Um
this turns out to break MUP. Um although
these can be removed in many cases
without necessarily uh hurting you. And
so maybe it's not such a bad idea but
this does seem to break MUP. Um it also
seems to break if you use more exotic
optimizers like Lion which basically
rely on the sign of the gradient. And
this is sign gradient is kind of like
spiritually similar to muon and other
ideas. And so there might be other
interesting things that break with mu as
well. Um finally the thing that seems
most concerning is that if you do large
decoupled weight decay um you end up
with significant MUP failure. So this is
maybe the one stress test that it does
fail. Um
but to close out this final section you
know you might in the end ask like is
MUP useful? Um, and if you really want
to stabilize your learning rates, it is
actually pretty useful. Um, there's a
lot of experiments of this form where,
you know, if you increase the width,
your optimal learning rate shifts very
predictably, but, you know, very greatly
as a function of scale, whereas with
MUP, it doesn't. And so, it's one of the
many tools in the toolkit to try to
control hyperparameter drift as a
function of scale. Um, I think it's an
interesting open area of research. It's
not really sort of you know done and
dusted and like this is the one right
thing to do but there's a lot of promise
in the sort of the MUP style
initialization program there's also a
lot of promise in just fitting scaling
laws as well
okay so final thing I want to close with
you know scaling in the wild is very
tricky as I sort of mentioned in one of
my replies you know I think the initial
presentation of scaling laws makes it
sound like a science right like it's
like yes draw this line do these
procedures and you will know for sure
what will happen at scale Um but I think
in reality it's a lot more messy and a
lot more unknown than that. Um you know
there are lots of things that people do
use and practice scaling loss for like
picking architectures, picking
optimizers, picking hyperparameters,
right? All of these things are things
that people do with scaling loss, but
there is really an art to it in the
sense of you don't really know if it's
truly going to extrapolate forever. You
want to do sort of reasonable things to
maximize the chances of success, right?
And so there's lots of solutions that
people have. You can use MUP, you can
search for the optimal learning rate and
all these other kinds of things. And
these are ways of controlling uh
hyperparameter drift. But there's no
silver bullet yet. Maybe next year there
will be a module that's like we've
solved it, but not quite yet.
Great. Thanks a lot. Uh I can take
questions afterwards.